Guide to the William Manchester Papers, 1934 - 2004
William Manchester Papers1934 - 2004
Special Collections & Archives, Wesleyan University
Manchester, William, 1934-2004
1000-169
327
470
William Manchester (1922-2004) was a noted author of eighteen books and dozens of articles. His first book, Disturber of the Peace, was a biography of H.L. Mencken published in 1951. Manchester wrote three novels during the 1950s, after which he published A Rockefeller Family Portrait in 1959, based on a series of magazine articles on John D. Rockefeller and the two generations that followed him. Manchester wrote one more novel before returning to non-fiction in 1962 with Portrait of a President, a study of John F. Kennedy. Manchester suddenly rose to national prominence in 1964 when Jacqueline Kennedy selected him to write the authorized account of John F. Kennedy's assassination. Robert F. Kennedy was also closely associated with the project. Two years later, Mrs. Kennedy sued Manchester to prevent its publication, setting off a controversy that played out on the front pages of newspapers around the world. Following a settlement, The Death of a President was published in 1967. With his reputation established, Manchester steadily published works of non-fiction: The Arms of Krupp (1968) chronicled the German munitions family; The Glory and the Dream (1974) provided an analysis of American history, 1932-1973; Controversy and Other Essays in Journalism (1976) included Manchester's own account of the Death controversy; American Caesar (1978) profiled Gen. Douglas McArthur; Goodbye, Darkness (1980) was Manchester's memoir of his World War II Pacific combat experiences; The Last Lion (1983 and 1988), a two-volume biography of Winston Churchill; and A World Lit Only By Fire (1992), an overview of the Middle Ages and Renaissance. Manchester was associated with Wesleyan University for more than 40 years, first as an editor for American Education Publications (the publisher of My Weekly Reader and other periodicals formerly owned by the University) starting in 1955, and later as a writer-in-residence and adjunct professor.
Correspondence, manuscript drafts, proofs, galleys, extensive research and reference materials, photographs, and other documentation relating to Manchester's professional career, his eighteen books and dozens of articles and other writings, and personal affairs, including his college years, awards, speeches, financial and legal matters, the construction of his Middletown house, and travels. Also includes scrapbooks, audio and video tapes and computer files, and realia.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
No restrictions, except for certain materials related to The Death of a President. A 1967 judgment and decree defines such material as:
(1) the Manuscript; (2) any writing of which Manchester is the author which ever was, or was intended by him to be, part of any version of Manchester's proposed work of which the Manuscript is one version; (3) written notes made by Manchester personally in the course of preparation of the Manuscript during the period March 26, 1964 through April 15, 1966 of interviews or conversations between Manchester and any member of the plaintiff's [Jacqueline Kennedy Onassis was the plaintiff] family (which term, as used in this Judgment and Decree, shall include the family of the late President John F. Kennedy) or members of her household (which term, as used in this Judgment and Decree, shall mean and include all persons at any time prior to April 15, 1966 in the personal employ of the plaintiff or the late President John F. Kennedy and those who served at any time during the administration of the late President John F. Kennedy as members of the White House household staff, such as maids, butlers, valets, gardeners, nurses and all others performing essentially personal or household services for the President and his family, or as personal secretaries, or as members of the Secret Service or White House police attached, in whole or part, to the President or members of his family personally); (4) tapes or other voice recordings, furnished to or possessed by Manchester, of plaintiff or members of her family or members of her household, and all copies, excerpts, fragments, transcripts, abstracts and summaries of any of the foregoing; (5) letters or written communications from the late President to plaintiff, from plaintiff to the late President, and between and among the plaintiff, the late President, any members of her family and any member of her household, and all copies, abstracts and summaries of any of the foregoing; (6) the items mentioned in the subdivisions (4) and (5) hereof shall be limited to such items therein described as were furnished to, or obtained by, Manchester during the period March 26, 1964 through April 15, 1966. [Complete judgment and decree found in box 56 folders 33-34]
Additionally,
The undersigned hereby agree that they shall treat as if they are 'material', subject to the provisions of the Judgment and Decree, all notes of interviews, letters or other communications of the following: Robert S. McNamara Kenneth P. O'Donnell David Powers Pierre Salinger occurring during the period March 26, 1964 to April 15, 1966, which concern the actions, conduct or statements of Mrs. John F. Kennedy or her children during the period November 22, 1963 through November 30, 1963. [Signed Jacqueline B. Kennedy; William Manchester; Harper & Row, Publishers, Inc. by Cass Canfield. Box 56 folder 30.]
This material is restricted until 2067 January 17. The container list below details some of the material that is restricted; otherwise, separation sheets will be found in the papers.
Acquisitions Information
Bequest of William Manchester, 2004.
Biographical Note
William Manchester was a well-known figure on the Wesleyan University campus for more than forty years, serving first as an editor of university publications, then as a fellow of the Center of Advanced Studies, later as adjunct professor of history and a writer-in-residence, and, finally, as adjunct professor emeritus. After enjoying modest success writing fiction and nonfiction books in the 1950s, he suddenly rose to national prominence in 1964 when Jacqueline Kennedy selected him to write the authorized account of John F. Kennedy’s assassination. Two years later, she sued him to prevent the publication of The Death of a President, setting off a controversy that played out on the front pages of newspapers around the world. Manchester—protégé of H. L. Mencken, newspaper man, foreign correspondent, and best-selling author—profiled larger-than-life figures, including John F. Kennedy, General Douglas MacArthur, and Winston Churchill, and chronicled contemporary American history.
William Raymond Manchester Jr. was born in Attleboro, Massachusetts on April 1, 1922. His parentage bridged the Mason-Dixon Line; his mother’s family was from Virginia, his father’s family from Massachusetts. They met when his father was recuperating in Norfolk from disabling wounds sustained as a marine during the First World War. In spite of physical handicaps, the senior Manchester was an independent and capable man who became the Western Massachusetts supervisor of public welfare. The father’s expectations had a lasting influence on his eldest son. Manchester Jr. had one brother, Robert, fourteen years younger.
Manchester started school in Attleboro, Massachusetts, continuing in Springfield, Massachusetts after the family moved there. Although not physically strong, he was an active Boy Scout, attaining the rank of Eagle Scout. He attended Springfield Classical High School, where he was active in drama. A natural leader, he directed plays and also acted in them. His writing skills were already evident in his re-working of a play by de Maupassant, The Necklace, to be broadcast on the radio and in his modernization of Oliver Goldsmith’s She Stoops to Conquer. He graduated from high school in June, 1940. Manchester entered Massachusetts State College (now known as the University of Massachusetts) in September, 1940. As a freshman, he pledged to the Lambda Chi Alpha fraternity and was subjected to the usual hazing. His letter to the editor of The Collegian takes issue with that custom, but he joined the following year. In January of Manchester’s freshman year, his father died. Although he was grieving, Manchester returned to college for the spring semester. He tried his hand at poetry and represented Massachusetts State College at a poetry-reading contest in May, 1941. In his sophomore year, he was on the staff of the college literary magazine, The Collegian Quarterly, and became assistant editor in his junior year. He also wrote for the college newspaper, The Collegian. His love of words is evident in a well-worn dictionary given to him in 1941. It traveled with him his whole life; the front endpapers document his various addresses in Amherst, Baltimore, and Middletown. Manchester was an avid football fan, then and in his many years at Wesleyan. The school songs that he obviously enjoyed were reflected later in his books in his use of popular songs to evoke the spirit of the times.
In the summer of 1942, after his sophomore year, Manchester enlisted in the Marines, perhaps as a tribute to his father. His reserve status allowed him to complete his third year of college, but at the end of this time, in July, 1943, he was sent to Dartmouth College for training in the newly-created V-12 program. This program allowed recruits to continue their education while creating a pool of potential officers for the Navy and Marines. (Wesleyan also hosted a V-12 program at that time.) Manchester’s program was completed in November, 1943. From New Hampshire, he went to Parris Island, South Carolina, for boot camp; Quantico, Virginia, for officer candidate school (he was never commissioned); and then to Camp Lejeune, North Carolina, for an advanced combat intelligence course.
On August 1, 1944, he was shipped out to the Pacific Ocean island of Guadalcanal, where he endured eight more months of training in tropical jungle conditions. On April 1, 1945—-his twenty-third birthday-—he was sent to Okinawa. For the next two months, he witnessed war at its worst. His unit was part of the force that took Sugar Loaf Hill at the end of May. Shortly after that, he was lightly wounded and hospitalized but quickly left the hospital to rejoin his unit. His war journal was eerily predictive. He wrote about how much he looked forward to being back, and yet, if you keep running the target up, sooner or later it’s going to get hit. He was seriously wounded on June 4, 1945, evacuated to Saipan, and honorably discharged on October 24, 1945. He returned home to his mother in Oklahoma City.
Pursuing his interest in journalism, he took a job as a copy boy at The Daily Oklahoman and quickly became a hospital and police reporter for the newspaper. Although he enjoyed the work, after four months, he decided to return to Massachusetts State College for the spring ’46 semester to finish his degree. In this last semester, he was chosen to be class orator and received a letter of congratulations from the president of the college. He graduated on June 10, 1946. Later that year, he met and became friends with John F. Kennedy during his first campaign in Boston.
The end of college is often a time of false starts and uncertainty. Manchester applied to the school of journalism at Columbia University but was denied admission. He also became engaged to Elinor Palmer, although no wedding date was set. They were never married. Two years later, on March 27, 1948, he married Julia Brown Marshall, to whom he was married for fifty years.
Manchester was accepted in the journalism program at the University of Missouri and moved to Columbia, Missouri, to begin the one-year program. He graduated with a master of journalism degree on August 29, 1947. His thesis was titled, A Critical Study of the Work of H. L. Mencken as Literary Critic of the Smart Set Magazine, 1908–1914. In the process of writing it, he had met Mencken and the two men had hit it off. Manchester wanted to write Mencken’s biography, Mencken agreed, and the end result was that Manchester moved to Baltimore just after graduation, in September, 1947. Mencken had arranged for him to be a reporter at the Baltimore newspaper, The Sun, so he would have an income while he was writing the biography. According to a letter from Mencken to Manchester’s mother, Manchester fit in well and was well-liked. Mencken was known as a caustic observer, but he wrote a charming letter.
Manchester’s skills as a reporter and a writer led to a series in 1951 on the state of Baltimore’s hospitals. Health care was a topic that had interested Manchester since his Daily Oklahoman days. The in-depth series was reprinted as a pamphlet, Our Hospitals Are Sick. In 1953, Manchester was assigned as foreign correspondent for The Sun to the Middle East, India, and Southeast Asia. He departed on January 23. With his unerring ability to be in the right place at the right time, he happened to be crossing the Atlantic on the same boat as Winston Churchill and was engaged by Reuters to send regular dispatches on the great man during the journey. In February, he met with the president of Egypt, General Muhammad Naguib. In March and April, he covered cities all over India. During this time, he was in correspondence with William Shawn of The New Yorker, who had expressed an interest in publishing some of his writing. Manchester met Adlai Stevenson in India and wrote about their meeting for The New Yorker. Unfortunately, he was rejected.
Manchester continued southeast, covering Burma, Thailand, and Southeast Asia in June. In July, he was taken ill. He received medical care in India but eventually was instructed to come home at the end of the month. He received many letters of sympathy on his illness and congratulations on his excellent reporting. His pieces from this trip were reprinted in the booklet Red Roads to Mandalay. Manchester sent copies of his work to important people he thought would be interested in them. E. M. Forster, for example, thanked him for three articles on India. Such initiative often bore results and it was a habit Manchester maintained throughout his writing career.
Back in the United States, Manchester recuperated during the fall of 1953 and spring of 1954, continued as a reporter for The Sun, and started work on a novel. Later, he would write about the summer of ’54: It was now becoming difficult to work evenings after a long day, however, and when Mencken offered me a position which would permit me to start my writing day in the afternoon, I quit the paper. For a year, Manchester read to Mencken in the mornings, and worked on his novel in the afternoons.
In the summer of 1955, Manchester was hired by American Education Publications (AEP) to be assistant managing editor of high school periodicals for the Department of School Services and Publications. Wesleyan had acquired AEP, publisher of My Weekly Reader, in 1949. This organization rapidly expanded to produce thirteen school periodicals with a circulation of 16.5 million. Manchester moved to Middletown in June,1955 and was soon promoted from assistant to managing editor. He was responsible for six weekly news reviews, among them Current Events. In 1958, he applied for, and was granted, a Guggenheim Fellowship for the purpose of finishing his fourth novel. This fellowship ran from July, 1959 to July, 1960. In 1959, he was also invited to be one of the first fellows in the Wesleyan Center for Advanced Studies, now known as the Center for the Humanities.
* * *
Appropriately enough, Manchester’s first book was devoted to the life of a writer. Disturber of the Peace: The Life of H. L. Mencken, published in 1951, helped establish Manchester’s reputation as a new talent and was reviewed in major publications across the country. While some reviewers felt that Manchester’s view of Mencken was not entirely objective, many appreciated his research and writing abilities.
Manchester then shifted to fiction, writing four novels in eight years that relied heavily on his real-life experiences. The City of Anger, published in 1953, looked at big-city corruption in a city that resembles Baltimore; Shadow of the Monsoon, published in 1956, drew on his foreign correspondent days in India; Beard the Lion, published in 1958, was a political thriller set in the Middle East; and The Long Gainer, published in 1961, told the story of a political and athletic scandal at a state university. Although they generally received good reviews, these novels were not huge sellers. Today, we can see that they are representative of Manchester’s writing technique: voluminous research, a mastery of detail, and careful writing and revision.
Also in the 1950s, while a full-time employee of the Baltimore Sun and later AEP, Manchester developed a successful freelance career writing magazine articles for such publications as The Nation, Look, The Reporter, and Harper’s. He wrote steadily for Holiday on a wide variety of topics, ranging from a journey down the Connecticut River, to the Spanish American War, to profiles of famous Americans. In 1955, he even tried his hand at drama, adapting City of Anger for a television play called The Takers, starring Ed Begley.
A series of articles on the Rockefellers led to his 1959 book A Rockefeller Family Portrait, and his series of articles profiling President John F. Kennedy led to his 1962 book Portrait of a President. While researching Portrait, Manchester went to the White House to interview JFK. With Portrait of a President completed, Manchester turned to what he thought would be his next book, a history of the Krupp munitions family.
Kennedy’s assassination in Dallas on November 22, 1963, changed all that. In early 1964, JFK’s widow, Jacqueline Kennedy, decided that an authorized version of the events surrounding her husband’s death should be written. Remembering her husband’s appreciation for Portrait of a President, she wanted to know if Manchester would be willing to take on the project. Later, he would ask, how could he turn down the widow of the fallen president? He had already taken a leave from Wesleyan in early February, 1964, to work on the Krupp book. That project promptly got shelved.
Instead, in March, he headed for Washington, D.C. for meetings to discuss the new book with John F. Kennedy’s brother, Robert. The two reached an agreement covering the scope of the project. No one wished to profit from the national tragedy—Manchester agreed to limit his share of royalties to no more than $40,000 for the book, with the remainder of the profits going to the formation of a Kennedy presidential library. The publisher, Harper & Row, agreed to take only necessary expenses.
Manchester would be granted exclusive access to the Kennedy family, which encouraged all parties to participate in Manchester’s research. Robert F. Kennedy and Jacqueline Kennedy would have the right to review the book for publication, which, at that time, was scheduled for 1968, five years after the President was killed. On March 29, 1964, Robert Kennedy released an official announcement, and Manchester immediately embarked on gathering research on what would become The Death of a President.
Manchester left no stone unturned and amassed thousands of pages of research materials. He conducted hundreds of interviews, including sessions with Jacqueline Kennedy and Robert Kennedy. I approached every person who might shed light upon this complex of events. Manchester later wrote. I went over every motorcade route, searching for men and women who had been spectators, and in Dallas I walked from Love Field to the overpass, looking for potential sniper’s nests. Every scene described in the book was visited. I crawled over the roof of the Texas School Book Depository and sat in Oswald’s sixth-floor perch. In Washington, Hyannis Port, and elsewhere I studied each pertinent office, embassy, and home—over a hundred of them.
By March, 1966, Manchester had completed a 1,200-page draft. It was, for him, a gut-wrenching experience, but he was proud of his work. He wrote letters to Robert Kennedy and Jacqueline Kennedy informing them that he had finally finished. Then, he packed an original and four carbon copies of the manuscript in a suitcase, took a bus to New York City, and personally delivered them to his agent and RFK’s office. Robert Kennedy designated two of his close advisors, Edwin Guthman and John Seigenthaler, as reviewers of the manuscript. Harper’s editor, Evan Thomas, read a copy. Manchester also sent a copy to Arthur Schlesinger, who had served President Kennedy. Through the spring and early summer of 1966, manuscript drafts criss-crossed the country. Many cuts were suggested to meet a variety of concerns represented by the different viewpoints of the reviewers.
Manchester began to grow concerned that final agreement would be difficult to reach, and he feared Robert Kennedy might delay approval of publication. Manchester pressed RFK to send definitive word that the publication would go forward, and it finally arrived in the form of a telegram on July 29. At the same time, a draft was agreed upon, and with things apparently buttoned up, the manuscript went out to a half dozen magazines that had expressed interest in serialization. A bidding war developed between Look and Life. Look offered the most money, control of the presentation to Manchester, and perhaps most importantly, RFK felt that Look had been a friend to the Kennedy family, unlike Life. Manchester signed a contract with Look in early August, 1966, giving him the then-record sum of $665,000 for a magazine serialization. Manchester remarked afterwards that the Look money enabled him to pursue whatever projects he wanted for the rest of his life.
Up until this point, Jacqueline Kennedy had been a willing, if distant, participant in the process, but the announcement of the Look serialization seemed to disturb her. She had not read the book, and, in fact, she had been advised by Manchester and others that she shouldn’t because she would find it too upsetting. Her sense, perhaps, had been that the book would get written, published, and then sit on a shelf somewhere. Apparently, she found the idea that Manchester would receive $665,000 and that the book would be serialized and available to millions of readers to be upsetting; at least, that wasn’t what she had in mind when she initiated the project.
This was a real surprise to Manchester, his editor, his agent, Robert Kennedy, and RFK’s advisors. Richard Goodwin, another former President Kennedy man, was brought in as Mrs. Kennedy’s representative, and he and Manchester attempted to appease Mrs. Kennedy. It was not until the three met in Hyannis Port in early September that Manchester realized how Mrs. Kennedy truly felt about the serialization. Nonetheless, through September and October, 1966, the parties dug in: Look and Harper insisted they had valid contracts, Manchester believed he had RFK’s approval to go forward, and Mrs. Kennedy believed that the serialization should be cancelled.
The tortuous work on the book and serialization continued into November. Galleys from Harper and Look were produced and gone over by the parties. Harper and Manchester agreed on a publication date of April,1967 and in a concession to Mrs. Kennedy, Look cut back its planned seven-part series to four, commencing in January, 1967. Manchester diligently argued, edited, argued, re-edited, and edited again, trying to maintain the integrity of his work while meeting the demands of reviewers he viewed as unnecessary and unreasonable.